Okay, I think we will get started, right. So, next we will see the graph coloring based
register allocation, right. So, this is where we were. So, in doing global register allocation,
the idea is to essentially make sure that two variables whose live ranges overlap, they
are allocated different registers, right. So, this information about which live ranges
are overlapping with which other live ranges can be captured in the form of a graph, right.
So, you can actually graph with nodes representing these variables and two variables kind of
conflict with each other or their live ranges overlap with each other, then you can actually
between them, right. So, that is essentially what you are going to call this graph as the
interference graph and in the interference graph, nodes represent the variables, right.
That that have to be allocated registers and edges between these variables essentially
represent whether there is a conflict between those two variables or not, okay. So, there
is an edge between V 1 and V 2 if V 1 and V 2 conflict with each other. That means
that the live ranges of these overlap or they are live at the same time. Then this register
allocation problem itself will turn into what is called the graph coloring problem.
Given a graph, we want to color all the nodes of the graph such that, right, two nodes do
not have the same color if they have an edge between them, right. That is called the graph
coloring problem, right. So, also chromatic number, right, what is the minimum number
of colors that are required to color the graph, right. So, if you find the minimum number
of colors that are required to color that graph or if you find out whether k colors
can be used to color that graph, right, that is essentially a graph coloring problem, okay.
Now, given a machine with k registers and given a program, if we can actually construct
the interference graph for that program and then ask the question can this graph is k
colorable, is this graph k colorable. And if it is yes, then we can actually allocate
registers for all the variables in that particular graph. If the answer is no, then of course,
not all variables can be allocated this, but some of them can be allocated and the
remaining have to be used from the memory, right.
So, if the k coloring is possible, then based on the color, those variables or those nodes
which have the same color are assigned to the same register and all the variables are
assigned these colors, okay. Now, let us see how, what is the complexity of this graph
coloring algorithm, right. The complexity of coloring a graph with color greater than
3 is NP-hard, okay. And therefore, we have to use heuristic approach to solve this problem,
okay. Now, before we go to the heuristic, we will also ask the question what if the
graph is not k colorable or what if the graph is k colorable, but we are not able to find
that coloring, right. What do we do in those cases? In those cases, of course, we have
to spill some of the variables and those variables will be from memory and the remaining variables
will be from the registers. So, essentially given a code, we want to construct the interference
graph for that code and then see whether the graph can be colored using k colors.
And if they can be colored using k colors, then what are the colors that need to be assigned
for these different nodes? That essentially tells which registers are being assigned to
what variables and which variables share the same register. All of this is basically obtained
by doing the graph coloring problem, correct. That is really what we want to do. If it is
not k colorable, then which registers or which variables, sorry, which variables are going
to come from memory, which variables are actually going to be spilled, correct. And those variables
which are spilled, how do we handle them, right.
Okay. Now, let us take a bigger example than what we saw earlier, okay. Here I have a sequence
of instructions and as you can see that this sequence of instruction has some conditional
branches and labels and things like that. So, this is no longer a single basic block,
correct. It is not a single basic block because there is a branch instruction here and there
is a branch instruction here and there are jumps into this code, right, isn't it.
So, this is basically a piece of code which is represented using this control flow graph,
right. So, this set of instruction form one basic block. These two instructions form another
basic block. This forms a basic block and this one forms a basic block, right. However,
when you take this control flow graph and then write it as a linear sequence of instruction,
right, it is going to be in one of these two forms. Either you put this instruction first
and then branch to this and then subsequently this instruction and then code further or
you go this way and then this and then this, right. So, you have to linearize it in some
form, right. So, basic block B 1, B 2, B 3 and B 4 or basic
block B 1, B 3, B 2 and B 4, correct. So, this is going to be the sequence of instructions
and this is the corresponding control flow graph, okay. Now, let us see what happens
in terms of live ranges, right. So, S 1, S 2, S 3, S 4 up to S 6 are the temporary variables
that we are talking about to which registers need to be allocated, right. So, here are
the live ranges for these variables and the important thing to look at is first let us
look at S 1. S 1 is being defined here and is used by these instructions and this is
the last use of S 1. After this in this code there is no use of S 1. So, the live range
of S 1 is from this point to this point, correct. What about the live range of S 2? The live
range of S 2, so live range of S 2 is from here, right, till this point, okay, till this
point, okay. Well, let us take it live range of S 2 is up to here and then it is not being
used anywhere in this basic block. It is not even used in any of these two basic blocks
and only used here, right. In other words what happens is that S 2 starts
its live range here, but its last use is at this point in time. So, if I consider let
us say a point here, technically speaking there is a definition of S 2 prior to this
and there is an use of S 2 after this. So, that means that the live range of S 2 is from
here to here even though it is not being used in either of these basic blocks, right. So,
technically speaking the live range of S 2 is something like this, but it goes I think
the some coloring is kind of missing in my thing. So, let us come to that, okay. It
is actually from here till here or you can think of this as having two live ranges, right,
with a break in between, right, also another way of thinking about it. We will see what
are the pros and cons of thinking in this way, what do we mean by the holes and other
things, okay. Whereas S 3 is being defined here and is continuously
being used in all of these basic blocks including up to this point. So, its live range is kind
of continuous from here to here, similarly for S 4, S 5 and S 6, right, yeah. So, what
we see here is that there is a hole in the use of S 2's live range in this point, right,
because these two basic blocks do not use S 2. We can think of this as having a hole,
but both of these variables are going to be recognized as S 2, right. So, let us stick
with that for the time being and then see. Now, we can see that S 1 interferes with S
2, it interferes with S 3, it also interferes with S 4, right. That means that there will
be an edge from S 1 to S 2, S 3 and S 4. S 1 does not interfere with S 5 or S 6, right.
Like that you have to identify, right, for each variable with what all it interferes.
So, for example, if I take S 5, it interferes with S 6, it also interferes with S 2, because
this is actually a live range of S 2. The live range of S 2 is from this point to this
point and again from this point to this point. You could have considered this as contiguous
across all of these points, but then there is a disadvantage to that, okay. So, we will
for the time being consider it like this, right.
Now, given this interference graph, the question is we can now ask is this graph 3 colorable,
right. Is this graph 3 colorable? The answer is no. I do not know how you got it, but let
us say it is no, okay. Okay, there is a clique having four nodes, right. So, it has to be
four colorable. It has to be at least four colorable or it has to have at least four
colors to color it, right. Okay, now let us ask this question. Is it four colorable? No.
No. Yeah, in this one I have not shown S 2, S 2 S 5, okay. Yeah, S 2 S 5 I have shown,
right. S 2 S 5 there is an interference. S 2 S 6 there is an interference, yes. Is it
four colorable or no? Yes.
So, those who are saying no, those who are saying no are on this side and those who are
on this side, is it? Okay, so let us see if it can be colored using four colors, right.
Is that a valid coloring? For this interference graph, it is a valid coloring, right. You
only need four colors. You do not need five, right, because these two nodes have to have
colors which are other than red. This has to have color which is other than red, blue
or yellow, right and I can actually give the same color to this because these two do not
have a overlap, right. Problem? It is okay, right. So, this is four colorable. So, the
moment I identify this as four colorable and if I have four registers then I will give
register 1 to S 1, 2 to S 2, 3 to S 3, 4 to S 4 and again 1 to S 5 and then 3 to S 6.
I have to be careful because I should not allocate the same register which was given
to S 2 or I should not allocate this. Well, I could have allocated S 4 also for this,
but for this I should not have allocated S 4 or S 3 or S 2. I should only allocate S
4, right. So, to identify this coloring that problem for K greater than or equal to 3 is
NP hot, okay. Now, let us see how Chaitan's graph coloring algorithm works, right. Chaitan
was the first one who have kind of formulated this as a graph coloring problem and proposed
a solution to this. He made one key observation which is actually very simple. The sense that
you take the interference graph and if there is any node with a degree less than K, strictly
less than K, then you can remove that node and then color the rest of the graph, sorry,
and you can remove that node and you can keep applying this rule again and again and if
you are able to do this and then completely remove all the nodes from the graph then that
particular graph is K colorable, right. So, what is the idea? Take the graph, find out
if there is an edge, if there is a node with degree less than K, then remove that node
along with all its edges, right. Keep doing this again and again and then if you are successful
in removing all the nodes from the graph then that graph is K colorable, right. Let us see
why this is true or why this helps, right. So, let us take, we take a graph G, right
and then remove one node which has degree less than K. The resulting node, resulting
graph let us call it as G prime, right. The question is if G prime is K colorable, then
G is also K colorable. Why? Because the node that you have removed only has K minus 1 edge
at most K minus 1 edges, correct. So, it will at least have one spare color other than
this K minus 1. That color can be given to that node, right. So, I have the graph G prime
and I have the node G, I mean I have the node N. This node has at most K minus 1 edges,
right. That means that it is going to be adjacent only to K minus 1 nodes and even if all of
these K minus 1 nodes have different colors, I have one more color to be given for this
node, correct. Therefore, if I color this graph with K colors,
I can color this entire graph also using K colors, got it, right. So, you can now eliminate
this particular node and now you can apply this idea again and again and then keep removing
nodes which are which have less than K edges, right. Why do we say strictly less than and
not less than or equal to? Because if it is equal to, then if the adjacent nodes all have
different colors, then there will be no color left for this, right. Therefore, in that case,
if it is equal to K, we cannot guarantee that the entire G can be colored using K colors.
But if it is less than K, then if G prime is K colorable, then G is also K colorable,
right. So, this is the simple observation that Chai then made and then using this he
proposed this graph coloring algorithm, right. So, let us see where this how this works and
right. Essentially, the idea is that you take the graph repeatedly, remove nodes which have
fewer than K colors, fewer than K edges, right. So, this step is what we are going to call
as the simplified step. Keep removing the nodes which have less than K edges, right.
If you end up with an empty graph, then we are done. The simplified step is over. If
you end up with a graph in which all nodes have degree greater than or equal to K, then
you cannot do simplify anymore, right. At that point in stamp, you have to take the
decision to spill a variable because now you have a graph which has in which every node
has K or more edges. That means that it cannot, it may not be K colorable. It may not be K
colorable, right. So, you decide and pick one node and then say that this node we are
going to spill. Then you remove that node with all the associated edges, right. Now,
you have a reduced graph. Now, again start doing your simplify operation. If you can
keep removing more nodes with you know edges a degree less than K, keep removing them.
If you end up again in a graph in which all nodes have K or more edges, then make one
more spill decision. Like this you iterate, right. You cannot, right. The processor does
not have more than K registers, right. You remember it. You are doing it for a specific
reason, right. Okay. So, yes. Not arbitrary. One of the nodes which has degree greater
than K, yes. Possibly. Among the nodes which have degree greater than K, which one to pick?
You are saying pick one with certain heuristics. Possibly. We will talk about that. We will
come back to that point, right. Okay. So, essentially the algorithm works in the following
way, right. Given a program, you compute all the live ranges, build the interference graph,
right. After you have built the interference graph, do this simplify operation. What does
simplify do? Keep removing nodes with degree less than or equal to, sorry less than K,
not less than or equal to, degree less than K. If the simplify process is completely over,
right. So, if you cannot simplify, then select a node and spill and then go back again and
then try to do simplify. And if you cannot do again, do this process. After having done
this, then what you are going to do is that we are once you have simplified the entire
graph, right. After this entire process, you would have simplified and you would have got
all the nodes being removed. We need to do the coloring part which is not described in
this diagram. I will talk about that later and that is really what is called the reverse
path. This figure has been wrongly drawn, okay. We will talk about that. So, here is
the algorithm for doing this, okay. Before I go into that, maybe I can just talk about
it here. So, what I do is that whenever I do simplify, what did I say? You can remove
a node from the graph and if it has less than K edges, then we know that if the rest of
the graph can be colored, then this can be colored, correct. So, that means that when
I want to color this graph, first I should color this part and after having colored this
part, I can come and color this node. Then I remove one more node and I have some other
graph. What do I say? Color that remaining graph, color this node and then color this
node. So, what we are going to do is that we are going to color the node in the reverse
order in which they have been simplified. That means the first one which I have removed
would be the last one to be assigned a color, correct. That means that I need to use some
kind of a data structure to remember in what order I am removing the nodes. Since I am
going to color them in the reverse order, the obvious data structure is a stack. So,
as you keep removing the nodes, you keep pushing them into a stack with an annotation saying
that whether this is removed because you have fewer than k edges or you have removed
it because you decided as a spill candidate, correct. So, these are the two possibilities.
Whenever you remove a node, you remove it because it has fewer than k edges. Therefore,
there is no spill that is required for that. But if you have removed it because no other
nodes can be removed, you chose this as a spill candidate, then it is going to be spilled.
So with that information, you actually push it into a stack. Now, sorry, yeah, go ahead.
Instead of removing from the graph, can you merge two nodes?
You may not be able to merge two nodes, right, because these may be two different variables.
They may be having different values, right. But hold on to your question of merging. It
is actually a…
It is the same register.
Yeah, you cannot, yeah, okay. So, let me ask you the question in the following way. So,
two nodes represent two different variables. When can you say that they will, they can
be merged?
They have all the same numbers and there is no less connecting there.
No, no, no, do not think of this just as a graph, okay. The graph also has a meaning,
right. One of them is S 1, variable S 1. Another is variable S 2. Can I say S 1 is
equal to S 2? S 1 has computed something. S 1 maybe has computed i plus 4. S 2 has computed,
let us say j times 4. Are these two variables the same? Temporary is the same. How can I
merge them? I cannot. Strictly speaking, I cannot. But there is a point in what you said.
If they have the same value, correct, then I can merge them. If they evaluate the same
thing, then I can merge them, right. That is possible. That we will talk about it little
later, right. So, that is why you cannot say that if node 1 and node 2 are connecting to
the same set of edges, I can merge them. No, because these two are two different variables.
They possibly hold different values, right. If I merge them, then my program is different,
correct. Yes, sir. Okay. So, what we are going to do is that during the simplify phase as
we keep removing the nodes, we are going to push them into the stack with the annotation
whether they are removed because they have fewer edges or because they are spill candidates.
Then when you want to color them, you pop these nodes from the stack and then color
them. And as you color them, you keep adding these edges back into the graph and then see
how new colors can be assigned. So, we will go through that process, right, using an example.
But before that, here is this entire algorithm, okay. So, in the forward pass, what you do
is that you after, so first step is of course building the interference graph. Then you
keep doing this repeatedly. If G has a node V such that its degree is less than K, right,
number of neighbors is less than K, then you can do the simplify step, remove this node,
push it into the stack and say there is no spill for this node, right, that this is going
to be allocated a register, right. After this step, you delete the node V along with all
the edges, all the edges that are incident on V, right. And you keep doing this. As long
as you can do simplify. If you end up in a sub graph in which all nodes have K or more
edges, right, that means that G is non-empty and every node has a degree greater than or
equal to K at this point in time. Then you choose a node for spilling. You can actually
choose a node which is least profitable, right, not necessarily an arbitrary node, but the
one which is, which incurs minimum cost. That can be decided using various heuristics,
right. And then you say that that is a node which is going to be spilled. Push that node
into the stack, right, and then say that this is a spill node, right, and then delete that
node along with all its incident edges. And after you have done this, you go back here
and then you start doing this. So, there is a, remember there is a repeat until loop here,
okay. So, once you remove one node for spill, again you try to see if you can simplify.
If you can simplify, keep doing that. If you cannot, come back and then spill one more
node and keep doing this until the entire graph, all the nodes in the graphs are removed.
As and when the nodes are being removed, they are being pushed into the stack, okay. In
the reverse pass which is the coloring pass, which is what I have not indicated in the
diagram, right. In the coloring pass what we are going to do is that we are going to
pop each node from the stack and then see the tag. If the tag is no spill, then we have
to allocate a register, right. We allocate a register by considering all the edges, right,
that we have removed and then see to which nodes it is incident on, right. Obviously,
since we have removed it and pushed it into the stack with a no spill, right, at this
point in time it will only have fewer than k neighbors. Therefore, we can allocate the
color which is not being assigned to any of its neighbors, right, at this point in time.
It may eventually have more than k neighbors, but at this point in time as we have popped
the node there is a sub graph that we have. It will only have fewer than k, so I can
always assign a color for this, right. So, that is really what we are going to do, but
if the tag says that it is spill, right, then it is a spill node. I will mark v as not being
allocated a register and I will reintroduce all the edges, okay and I will continue to
do this until the stack becomes empty, all right. Let us see how this works. Any questions
before we go into the details, right.
So, the coloring process is very simple. You pop the element from the stack, see if it
has a tag spill or no spill. If it has a tag spill then of course, you are going to say
that this is not going to be allocated a register, introduce the node and all its incident edges.
If it says no spill then what you need to do is you introduce all the incident edges
and then see which are the nodes to which this is a neighbor to, right and you are guaranteed
that this will be less than k, right. That is why you have removed this node and then
put into the stack saying no spill because it has only fewer than k nodes, right. At
most only k minus 1 colors would have been used. So, you can assign the kth color to
this or you can assign, yeah you can assign the kth color to it, right. That is really
how you color this and you keep doing this and then rebuild this interference graph completely.
By the time all the nodes would have been colored. So, let us see this in the form of
an example, okay but before we go into that let us talk about the complexity. Since you
are going to go through all the nodes one by one it is going to have a complexity which
is proportional to the number of nodes, okay.
And this is an algorithm which is actually used in many production compilers. Again there
are some positives as well as some negatives which we will talk about it little later,
right. We will take an example. So, in this particular case I am going to take this example,
and these are the live ranges for these variables and let us not worry how I have constructed
the interference graph but this is the interference graph, right because it will take you quite
some time to figure out all the edges and other things but you can go back and check.
For example if you want to look at B, right, node B interferes with M, E, C and D and also
K, right. So, you can see that M, E, C, D, J and K, okay, J also, right, J also because
I think J, yeah I think this is wrong. J should have been from here to here, sorry about that,
right. And remember this also talks about which variables are live out. So, for live
out variables we would like to keep them in the register so that live range is also being,
I mean that is shown by this extra point over here, extra program point over here, okay,
all fine. So, we have started off with this graph. Let us try to see if K colorable for
K equal to 4, right. Now pick any node arbitrarily which has fewer
than K edges, 4 edges, right. In this case I have picked H, I can remove that, I will
push it into the stack. Next one G, I can remove that. Next one K, F, right, E, I could
have removed M also because M has only 3 edges at this point in time, right. Then B, I can
remove D, right. Then of course J and C have 0 edges, I can remove them one by one, right.
So, as I keep removing them I have pushed them into my stack, right. So, you will see
this, right. So, this is finally what I have. Now I have to start coloring them. Since J
is the only node at this point in time I can give one color for this and then I will pop
this node. I have given the yellow color for this. Now the next node is C. I see what are
the incident edges on this. C and J originally did not have an edge between them. So, it
can also be given the same color, right. I can remove that. Then I introduce node D.
Node D has an edge to J as well as an edge to C. So, it has to be any color other than
the color of J or C. Fortunately for us J and C share the same color. Therefore, it
has to be any color other than yellow. So, let us say it was given red, right. Then the
next one, right. So, D has been now removed from the stack. The next one is B. You put
B, right and these are the edges. B has an edge to C, B has an edge to D and B has an
edge to J. So, it cannot be yellow. It cannot be red. So, let us give it a color blue. We
still have only used three colors. Then we remove B. We have the next node is M and M
has edges to B, C and D. Something is wrong. My coloring scheme has gone bad. So, this
cannot be red. This has to be green, okay. So, let us try to write it as green. Hopefully,
that will not cause a problem, but that is the only color I can give, right.
So, this has to be green because this cannot be yellow. It cannot be blue. It cannot be
red. Those are the three colors. So, it has to be green, right. Now, what about the next
node E? Bad, my bad, okay. But we will try to give a different color for E, okay. Let
us see. Maybe you can suggest me what color to be given for this. Yes, yeah, red or orange,
whatever we say, right. Remember, this is not red. This is green, right. That is why
we are changing this. So, this is red, not green. I became color blind when I was doing
this, okay, right, all right. Now, we can remove E also from our stack. Then the next
one is F and as you introduce F, now there is no problem, okay. Now, F is adjacent to
J, E and M. So, it cannot be green. It cannot be red. It cannot be yellow. So, we will give
blue for that. The next one is K, right. K is adjacent to B, D and J. Therefore, we
give a color which is other than blue, red or yellow. And then finally, we have G for
which we can give red and then H for which we can give blue, correct. So, effectively
we have colored this using four colors, right. This is how Chaitanya's algorithm works.
Now let us see what happens if we have three colors, right. Four, it is four colorable.
Let us see if it is three colorable, right. Of course, you only do for the number of registers
that are available in your architecture. But let us say I have another architecture in
which I have only three registers available. Then what happens in this example? We again
go through the same way. Now you remove only nodes which have two or fewer edges, right
because K is three. So, H can be removed, G can be removed, but then after this any
node at least has three edges. For example, yeah, every node has three or four edges or
even more. Nothing even has three. Everything has four edges. Well, F has three edges, correct.
C also has three edges, but they cannot be removed. K also has three edges. They cannot
be removed because we have only three registers. We have to take nodes which have fewer than
three. That means two or one, right. So, none of these nodes can now be removed. So, now
we have to take a call and spill. So, let us say somehow I pick node B for spilling,
right. So, now I push B with the tag spill, right. Now what happens? B can be removed.
Now do I have any node which has two edges? K. So, I can say K is no spill, remove K.
Then C is no spill, I can remove that. Then D. Then almost every node has now M. So, now
we have E, F, J, right. So, here we were trying to color this graph using three colors, but
then we have ended up with one node tagged as spill. So, Chaitan's algorithm essentially
says, you have a question? Do you have a question? Yeah.
You have chosen some other node other than B. Yes, very good. Yes. Possibly, possibly,
right. You can try with some spilling some other node and then, see I chose B because
B had more neighbors. By removing that, I am removing so many edges from that, okay.
But it may be the case that B may be required more often, in which case this may not be
a good decision. That is why you remember you asked the question. Instead of arbitrarily
spilling, now we may not necessarily arbitrarily pick a node. We may pick it slightly intelligently.
So one cost that was used by Chaitan in his algorithm is the number of times it is used
divided by the number of edges, okay. So, you are basically taking into account both
the usage and the number of overlap that it is causing. By doing that, you are actually
saying there is no guarantee that this will be optimal, but likely to be efficient. It
is a heuristic. So, what you say is correct. If you.
Again this is done arbitrarily in Chaitan's algorithm and that by itself can, well that
can influence to only certain extent. It will not influence in terms of whether something
becomes colorable or not colorable because that is decided by your thing, okay. So, it
does not affect any other thing other than what color goes where, okay, all right. Now,
let us start coloring this, right. Let us go through the reverse pass. Now, J has to
be given a color, right. So, let us give J yellow color and we give blue color to F,
although we could have, sorry, yeah, right, because there is an edge between J and F.
Next, we remove E because E is connected to both J and F. It has to be given a color other
than blue and yellow. So, these are the three colors that we have. We do not have green
anymore. Remember that. Now, I know why that became red. Okay, now, now let us look at
M next, okay. M is connected to E and F. So, it can be given the yellow color. D is connected
to J and M and it can be given the red color. C which is connected to D and M and it can
be given the blue color, right. Then K which is connected to J and D, right. These are
the connections that we have removed. Very good point, yes. So, somehow you have to remember
these edges that you have removed also or you can actually look at your original graph
and only connect those edges for the nodes that are already present, correct. So, for
example, B is not there. So, an edge between K and B need not have to be considered, right.
So, it need not have to be stored. You can actually infer it from other, correct. Now,
what, what is the next node? B. B is a spill node. So, it need not have to be allocated
any color. So, it is not being colored, but now keep introducing all the edges, right.
And of course, you have G which can be colored and H which can be colored, right. To go back
to your question, what would have happened if I have chosen a different color? See for
example, when I colored F instead of blue if I have chosen red, then the colors would
have cyclically gone around somewhere else, not necessarily cyclically. Some change would
have happened, but in terms of whether it is colorable or not colorable, no other change
would have happened. No additional cost would have changed, right. So, that coloring decision
can be pretty much arbitrary. Choose a color which is not used by any of the previous ones,
right. So, this graph we have colored it using three colors, but then we have to spill one
node, right. And we have chosen a node which possibly has the least cost, right. If B is
being used more often, then you should have chosen some other node, maybe E or maybe something
else, right at that point in time and then chose to spill that which might have caused
more nodes to spill, right, which might have caused. We do not know. It is a heuristic
algorithm, right. Yes.
Sir, it is still possible, this is not optimal for this matrix.
Definitely not optimal, yes.
Because in this case, it is still optimal.
But you cannot color this graph using three colors. That much is sure, right. I mean at
least this graph. In general, you cannot guarantee that, okay. I will give you an example little
later on, okay. A case where Chaitin's algorithm would say you need to spill, but you do not
necessarily need to spill. That is also possible. I will give you an example for that, right.
So, do you have a question Phil? Okay, it is not optimal. Definitely not.
And depending on what node you choose to spill, right, like what you pointed out earlier,
if I have not chosen B, but I have chosen something else like a E or a M, I may end
up spilling more nodes, right. I may end up, okay. So, the spill heuristic which we talked
about earlier is that you have to identify a node which gives you least cost. Chaitin
actually defined this cost to be the number of times the node is being used, okay. So,
the spill heuristics takes into account the cost which is the number of times the node
is being, the variable is being used and the degree which is the number of adjacent or
number of variables with which they interfere. It takes into account a combination of these
two costs and from what I understand, it is actually cost of n divided by degree of n.
So, the more degree you have, the fewer would be the overall cost or the fewer cost you
have, then also it will be more. So, if the cost is higher, then spilling that node is
not a good decision. If the degree is lower, spilling that node may not be a good decision,
may not be, right. So, it basically uses this ratio of cost to degree as the overall metric
by we saw, there you go. It is cost of n by degree of n and the one which has fewer cost
is what is chosen for spill at that point in time, okay.
Alright, any questions so far? Nan, right.
How will you get the cost?
How will you get the cost? Again, remember we talked about the usage based register allocation
method where we counting the, where we are counting the number of times each variable
is being used and where we are using the dynamic counts, something similar to that,
right. Alright, okay. Now, let us see some extensions to this, right. There are three
possible extensions that people have talked about. One is what is called the optimistic
spill. The other one is coalescing which you talked about and the third one is live range
splitting. We will introduce that also, right. So, optimistic spill is essentially that when
the graph cannot be simplified further, we remove one node as a spill node and then tag
it as spill. At that point in time we say that because I cannot simplify the graph,
I have to necessarily spill this. Why do I say that? Because even if I remove the node,
I cannot, sorry, I cannot simplify because in the reduced graph it has nodes which are
adjacent to this. It has at least k nodes which are adjacent to this and therefore by
removing this, I cannot guarantee that if the rest can be colored, this can be colored.
So, I am assuming that because it has k neighbors at that point in time, I may not have a free
color, but the k neighbors it has may not necessarily use k different colors. Some of
them can possibly use the same color in which case I may still have a color left out, right.
I will give you a very, very simple example where this becomes really obvious, right.
So, this Chaitin's algorithm was subsequently improved by Briggs who said that do not take
the decision of spill when you do the simplified step. Take the decision of spill when you
do the coloring step, okay. That means that you say that this may spill, right, but when
you are introducing the color, check all the neighbors. If you have, you know, k minus
1 different colors being used, then obviously this can be colored. But if you have k colors
being used for the adjacent nodes, then this cannot be colored, right. So, that is the
decision he says. So, that is Briggs algorithm, right. So, the actual spill decision is taken
during the coloring process, during the coloring phase, right. And when you push it into the
stack you say it may spill. Do not say it will spill, it may spill, right. So, here
is a very, very simple example. Is this graph too colorable? Yes, right. So, now if you
apply Chaitin's algorithm what happens? What is the simplified step? Can I simplify? Can
I remove any nodes? Each node has two edges, correct. So, I cannot simplify. If I have
applied Chaitin's algorithm, I would say spill a node, right. So, if I apply Briggs algorithm,
I am going to say that, okay, I have, I may have to spill a node. I still do not know.
So, let me pick a node, right. Maybe I have picked a in this case and then push it into
the stack and then say a may spill, right. I have not done anything very different. Only
thing is that instead of saying a spills, I am saying a may spill. Now, I have a graph
which can be simplified, right. And thought I can simplify it, simplify it, simplify it,
and remove all the nodes, right. Now, I start coloring it. When I color it using two colors,
B can be given a color, right. C can be, my coloring is not working. I think animation
will come later. Sorry about it. So, C can be given a color which is other than B. And
now what about B? B can also be colored which is a color which is other than C. So, I can
and that could be same as D, right. And now when you come to A, you see that A has two
neighbors B and D, but both share the same color. So, you still have one color left for
it. So, it can be colored. So, hopefully the colors know. Some of the coloring did not
come. Sorry about that, right. So, here you have, you can, you could have colored this
red, this would be green, this would be red, and this would be green. So, just because
a graph has all nodes and each of which having K or more edges does not mean that it is not
K colorable, right. It only says that it may be possible, it may be, it may happen that
one node has to be spilled, correct. That is all it says. So, Briggs algorithm essentially
says that take this decision of spilling not at the time of pushing it into the stack,
but at the time of popping it out. Because at that point in time, you know which are
the other edges which have already been colored and whether they have used K or fewer colors.
If they have used fewer than K color, then you can still color it using one of the remaining
colors. So, that is the change between the Briggs algorithm and the Chaitin's algorithm,
right.
So, next we will talk about a step called the coalescing, right. So, when we are coloring
this graph, we are assuming that, okay, there are these different variables and these variables
correspond to these nodes and I do not know anything about these nodes except about their
coordinates. But it may so happen that in my code, right, I would have two nodes which
are one is the copy of the other, right, something like this, right. For example, I have x is
equal to something and then I have written y is equal to x, right. Now, assuming that
these two are two different live ranges, I have one node for x and one node for y. If
I so happen, if it so happens that I have one node as a copy of the other node, right,
then in that case and only in that case, I can merge these two nodes, right. But then
when I merge these two nodes, the nodes which are adjacent to x and the nodes which are
adjacent to y will be adjacent to the union of that would be adjacent to x y. So, you
may increase the number of adjacent nodes, but still it is okay, right, still it may
give you better solution. So, this step is what is called the coalescing, right. So,
at some point in time, you go back and look at your code and then see if you find code
which is, that is when you generate your interference graph, you can actually say which of these
nodes are coalescible and which of them are not, right. They call it as move or non-move
nodes. For example, here y is basically called a move node because it is a move from move
of x to y, right. So, they kind of annotate it this way and then use this information
in coalescing node. And when you coalesce nodes, the number of interferences may increase,
but still it may help you to find solutions or color the things without having to go for
a spell. So, typically what they do is that they do the simplify pass, I think I have
this slide there, okay. So, you keep doing the simplify pass, right, and then you simplify
only non-move nodes, right. And then if you come to a situation where, okay, so, yes,
so simplify by removing all the non-move related nodes and if you come to a situation where
you cannot do simplify, but you have let us say move related nodes and if some of these
move related nodes can be combined, then you merge them, right. And then on the resultant
graph you try to apply simplify. If you can simplify, it is fine. If you cannot simplify,
try to see if you can do more coalescing, right. Keep doing this, okay, until you cannot
do any more coalescing or you cannot do any more simplify. If you cannot do simplify or
coalescing, then of course you have no option other than spill and then you come back and
then redo this whole thing again, right. So, that is how you can improve things, okay.
Now let us talk about the last optimization which is live range splitting, okay. So, again
I have a part of the example here. I did not do the full example for some reason, but let
us just try to see what it is and maybe with that, well with that we will kind of close
this graph coloring based allocation. So, every time you look at the live range and
then you see that two different variables are conflicting with each other and then you
take a decision of splitting, spilling a node, right. Whenever you cannot color, you take
the decision of spilling the node. Whether you do the spill at a time of pushing it in
the stack or you take the decision of spilling at a time of popping it from the stack, it
does not matter. You are only saying that this cannot be colored, we will give it a
different, I mean sorry, it cannot be colored, therefore it has to be spilled. One of them
has to be spilled. So, you take that decision anyway. So, this live range splitting approach
essentially instead of just choosing between, I mean instead of deciding it as spill, it
now goes back and then say should I spill or should I split. That is the decision you
try to take and wherever splitting incurs less cost, you will go ahead and do the splitting
as opposed to spilling. I will show you examples of this and you will understand what that
is, right. Again we will consider the same example that we saw earlier, okay and you
see that there is this gap, okay, for S 2 which is what I called as the hole, right.
Now, so this original graph is not three colorable, right, which we saw earlier. Now supposing
I say that this S 3 variable that you are looking at, right, has some use here, sorry,
it is being defined here but has no use here, correct, and has an use over here, right,
until here. So, let me try to decide and then say that I will split this live range S 3
into two parts, one part which is this and another part which is this, right. But if
I want to decide it to split here, what does it really mean? It means that at this point
in time I have to somehow get the value of S 3 again. So, it has some cost of spill versus
whatever it is, right, that cost is there. But let us try to think of that as a split,
right, then what happens, right. And similarly I will think of my S 2 as not as one live
range, right, going from here to here or this live range S 2 interfering with S 5 and so
on. But think of this as a fresh live range. That means that I will reload this value or
do something about it. Now when I do this, my interference graph changes to this. I have
all the original nodes but because of these split live ranges I have an S 2 prime and
S 3 prime. S 3 prime because I have split this live range into two parts and S 2 prime
because I am now considering these two live ranges as two different live ranges, okay.
In order for me to decide to do this there is a cost that I am incurring that I need
to calculate and I need to kind of evaluate whether this cost is worse than the spill
cost or better than the spill cost. If it is better than the spill cost then only I
should do this, okay. So the splitting decision again is taken based on whether the split
is going to be more, is less costly than the spill. Then only you do the split. So let
us look at having decided that, right, it is less cost and we are going to do the split.
How does it help to color? Okay, go ahead.
Yes and no, okay. Splitting has certain advantages as well. We will not go into that right now,
okay, right. So one thing is that, how do I put this? Yeah, it may appear to be somewhat
similar but let us let differ the discussion some other point, okay.
Yeah. S 2 prime and S 6 has two conflict, yes.
I think that edge is missing. But hopefully they will be given different colors. Let us
see what happens. They can be given different colors, right. Even though there is an edge
they can still be given different colors. We can correct it, okay, no problem, right.
So these are the optimizations or extensions that can be done to J. Tens algorithm. So
think of doing this optimistic spilling, think of doing this coalescing, think of doing this
live range splitting wherever it is possible, okay.
Now let us just briefly talk about local register allocation. This is typically done, typically
what is done is that it is global register allocation which is done and then in certain
cases where it is required you do some local register allocation which is essentially allocation
within a basic block. Let us see why this is useful or why this is simpler than the
other allocation. Now in local register allocation we are only considering register allocation
within a basic block, right. That means that within that basic block we are going to identify
what are the variables and what are their live ranges, okay.
Now the advantage here is that since it is a basic block there will be no notion of a
whole, right, because there is nothing like control flow graphs, right, the variable not
being used in this particular basic block which is kind of sequentially arranged and
because of that it is appearing to be together, etc., etc., right. Okay, I will maybe come
back and then talk about this point a little later but let us look at it in the following
way.
So I have these different variables S1 to S7 and their live ranges are shown here, right.
Now if I have to color this graph or if I have to, yeah, color this, I have not built
the interference graph because it may not be necessary to build the interference graph
here, but let us say if I build the interference graph and then I try to color it, how many
colors would I need, right. You can look at the graph and then say at what point in
time is the graph really fat, how many, means where more number of live ranges are interfering,
right. So you can see that at this point in time five live ranges are interfering. Again
at this point in time also five live ranges are interfering. Any other interval it is
only fewer than five. So if I have to color all of these variables without any spill,
how many registers would I require? Five. Five because it says that at this point in
time all these live ranges are interfering with each other. That means that I have a
graph with a click, right, a sub graph S1, S2, S3, S4, S5 with a click, right. Similarly
at this point in time I have a sub graph S2, S3, S4, S5, S6 with a click. So to color
them I need at least five colors, right. So in this case you can actually color this entire
graph without even constructing the interference graph because construction of the interference
graph is also expensive, right. It is actually O n squared depending on the number of variables
you set for which you want to construct the graph, okay.
So how do you color this particular graph? We will see that. So this local register allocation
is essentially within a basic block, right. And here as I mentioned earlier these live
ranges do not have any holes, correct. The interference graph in this particular case
if at all you construct they become what is called an interval graph. And these interval
graphs can be optimally colored, okay. And that problem is not NP hot, okay. So optimal
allocation can be done in linear time, right. And of course you can find out what is the
minimum number of colors that you need and that is given by the fatness of the graph,
alright.
Okay, now let us see how do we go about coloring this graph. So we can actually do the coloring
by starting going through these different points in time. And you only need to consider
the point in time when a live range starts. You do not even have to consider all other
points. So for example let us say I start with this live range S 1. So if all the live
ranges are kind of arranged in the ascending order of their start time then I can go through
each one of them at a time, right. So the first live range is S 1. I look at that start
point, right. And I have the available number of registers in a data structure called free.
So free has all the registers which are free at that point in time. So you start with the
live range whose start time is the lowest and keep going this in the increasing order,
right. And you only need to consider those points where a live range starts. Any point
of course in this example you have a live range starting at each one of those points.
So you will consider all the points. But in some other cases where you know a new live
range does not start you do not have to worry about that particular point, okay. So we assume
that when a live range ends its color can be free and that can even be decided at a
later point in time. So let us start off at the first point in which all the registers
are free. Here the fatness is 5. So if you want to color it you need 5 colors, right.
So we can give color 1 to S 1. The free colors would be the remaining colors. Then after
that when you come to S 2 you can give the second color to it, then the third color,
then the fourth color, then the fifth color. So far there is no problem. Now you have no
more free registers. But when you come to the next point you know that one is being
freed because its live range has ended. So one can be freed and that can go into the
free pool. Then you consider live range 6, variable S 6, it can be given the same color,
right. And then you consider the next live range S 7. By that time S 2 has finished.
So that register can be returned back and it can be assigned the color 2, right. So
this is how you color this. The essential advantage here is that you have these live
ranges which do not have pool, right. And because of that, right, you can actually go
through and because of that your interval graph is essentially your interference graph
becomes an interval graph and that makes your coloring process simple, okay.
Now let us see how this is useful. In fact this idea is more useful not only in doing
this local register allocation but this has also inspired one global register allocation
mechanism which is what is called the linear scan register allocation mechanism. Let us
talk about that next, right. So for global register allocation using graph coloring
you have to construct the interference graph and that is an expensive step in the register
allocation process, okay. And in many cases you may want to do this register allocation
or you may want to do code generation, right, and the time for doing the code generation
may matter. Okay let me give you one example, example of dynamic compilation just like you
talk about just-in-time compilation, right. When you do just-in-time compilation or dynamic
compilation what happens is that the compile time for compiling is actually a part of your
execution time, right. Are you familiar with languages which require dynamic compilation?
Yeah, one of them is Java.
Java, anything else?
. .
Let me give you a little bit for that, right.
.
Some Python implementations have that. That is what I was expecting you to say. Some R
implementations have that, right. So these are all things which were normally interpreted
languages but interpretation is very expensive. So during the execution you decide that you
will compile some part of the code and then when you try to compile these part of the
the code if you want to do register allocation for them you cannot be doing a very expensive
register allocation right. So, that the compile time for compiling the code is also an important
aspect right. So, that you need faster method for generating efficient code right. So, the
linear scan allocator is one such method which was actually proposed in 1999 and it uses
the notion of what is called the live interval ok. We will define what this live interval
is and this is being used instead of what is called the live range ok.
Now, we will explain this a little later on ok and because of this your register allocator
your global register allocator is actually going to look like a local register allocator
and it can be done in linear time or near linear time right that is the idea. So, let
us see what this is, but before we go to that let us first define what is the live interval
ok. So, for every variable we find the first point where it is defined and the last point
where it is used and irrespective of whether there are other control blocks or otherwise
we simply say that this variable is live from this point in the program to this point
in the program right. So, a live interval may include multiple live ranges. Remember
when we talked about the variable S 2 in the previous example it had a hole right and we
said that that hole is because there are these control flow paths control flow there are
these basic blocks in the control flow graph in which those variables are not being used
right. So, we were talking about that now what happens is that we do not kind of consider
these holes and consider this live interval as basically the combination of all of these
live ranges right. So, it is an approximation right it is a conservative approximation
of live ranges ok. Now, for the same example right now what happens
is that S 2 which is first defined here and is being used here its live interval is from
here to here whereas, when we talked about its live range we said that the live range
is from here to here and then from here to here right. In between we were thinking that
it is not live right because if I have taken this point sorry let us say if I have taken
this point in program I could have said that there are points which are where it is need
not have to be live right so that that was that ok.
Now, having approximated the live range with regard to the live interval now what happens
is that this graph now looks like your interval graph or looks like your interference graph
for basic block because there are no holes right. So, the interference graph for this
is something like this which is also what is called an interval graph ok. Now, this
graph can be colored in linear time but you do not even need to do that you can actually
go through the just like the way that you went through for the linear register allocator
and you can color it. So, we will see that algorithm next.
So, here since the fatness is 4 I have calculated it correctly right the fatness is 4 it requires
4 colors right and you see that it can be colored using 4 this is the click that we
talked about and ok. Now, let us see how the linear scan allocator works ok. So, first
thing is that you compute the live intervals for all the variables which is similar to
computing the live range but then it is an approximation and this can be calculated even
easier. Now, the interference among these live intervals ok if they interfere among
this then you assume that they cannot be given the same register ok. Now, the number of overlapping
intervals changes only at the start point and at the end points of the interval. So,
if you go back and look at this graph right if at some point in time the number of overlapping
intervals is 4 right it is going to be the same until either a live range finishes or
a new live range starts right it value is going to remain the same as long as no new
live range starts. For example, between this point and this point the number of live ranges
which are interfering with each other is exactly the same. At this point it is different because
this live range has ended at this point it is different because there is a new live range
starting. So, what happens in the linear scan allocator is that we will start worrying about
these points where the live ranges are starting that is really what this is saying ok. So,
it changes only at the start and end point of the interval ok. So, the linear scan allocator
uses the following data structures for doing this it uses what is called live intervals
ok which are basically all the variables and their live intervals, but they are stored
in the increasing order of the start point ok. It also maintains what is called an active
list which is basically the set of variables which are interfering at that point in time
to variables who have already been allocated registers ok.
This is stored in the decreasing order of the end points sorry in the this is stored
so the active list is stored in the again increasing order, but of the end points ok.
So we have two data structures both of them are sorted in the increasing order the first
one is started in the increasing order of the start point and the second one which is
the active list which is the set of variables which are interfering with variables which
have already been assigned a register right, but this is stored in the decreasing sorry
in the increasing order of the end points ok we will see why that is important ok.
So, the algorithm proceeds in the following way right you start with an initial active
list which is 0 because no register no live no variable has been assigned a register so
far so this is empty and in your live interval you have all the variables correct and those
variables are arranged in the increasing order of the start point. So, you take the first
interval in that thing that is the first live range ok. Now what you do here is that at
this point in time you expire any old interval that has expired ok initially this may not
kick in, but later on you will see that why this is useful right and then if you see the
length of active active is the all the live intervals which are interfering with variables
which have already been allocated registers right.
So, for example if I have allocated registers to four variables right and if I have allocated
active is four then it means that I have already used up four colors right and active will
only have intervals which are currently active that is why the name active any variable for
which a register has been assigned, but it interval is over will not be a part of active
right. So, that is essentially what you try to do in expire interval we will talk about
that little later on right. So, if you see that how many variables are currently active
and have been assigned registers and if that is equal to or the number of registers that
is available then at this point in time you have to do a spill right, but if it is less
than or then you have a register which is available. So, this interval is going to be
given that register by removing a register from the pool of free registers right because
there is some free register which is available and now add i to the active because now i
is an active interval and add it in the place. So, that it is the end time is always in the
increasing order active is end times are always in the increasing order.
So, this is how you go about this, but let us see what is expire interval expire interval
is that you at some point in time you are now looking at and then you look at what all
intervals have expired between the last time that you consider to now. So, for each interval
j in the active in the increasing order of the end time you keep looking at it if the
end point of j right is greater than the start point of i that means start of i is the current
point that you are talking about. So, if its end point is greater that means that the interval
is not is still live it is not over yet you do not do anything right, but if it is less
than this then you remove j from active and then whatever register j was given you release
it to the free pool. In fact, this need not even have to be continue because you can actually
break because you have seen one interval whose end point is greater than the current time
all other intervals will also be greater than the current time.
So, you do not need to do continue you could have done right. So, I am talking about this.
So, it is clear right what we are trying to do in expire intervals see remember in this
algorithm what you do is that you go from one start point to the next start point to
the next start point. So, when you go from one start point to another start point some
intervals may have finished. So, those finished intervals you are trying to remove from active
and we are trying to free that register and then put them back in the free register that
is really what we are doing. Now, again look at it. So, that is what expire
interval is about right. Now, what about this function spill at interval right you are going
to come to this function whenever all the registers are being used and then you have
one more live variable one more variable for which you want to see whether it should be
allocated register or not right. So, at that point in time you take a decision whether
this variable is going to be spilled or one of the variables which is in the active can
be spilled right. See active is all the variables which have been allocated registers which
is interfering with this particular time point right. If I decide that one of them can be
now spilled right I can give that register to this variable i how do I decide between
them I decide whichever interval which is shorter right sorry whichever interval which
is longer is the one which will be spilled. So, I compare the end point of i and the end
point of that register and then choose whichever one which is longer I will spill. So, this
is how the spill interval works right. So, I start off with the last interval in the
active because that has the highest end time if I check the end time of that with the end
time of the variable for which I need to allocate register whichever one is longer I choose
that as the spilling. So, if the end point of the last interval is greater than the end
point then I going to take the register back from that particular variable and give it
to i. So, I say register of i is register of spill and location of spill it gives you
a new location in the stack and then we remove spill from the active and we add i to the
active right. So, in this case what happens is that I will
again give you an example. So, what happens is that we have already allocated registers
right and we have now come to a new live range for sorry new variable for which we want to
see whether a register has to be given or not. Now, for all the live variables for all
the variables which are interfering with it find out whether the end point of this versus
the end point of any of this if the end point of one of them is longer than the last one
is longer than this then we decide to spill that one right or if the end point of this
is greater than all of those then we decide to spill this one again this is a heuristic
right if you decide to spill then if you decide to spill one of the existing active variables
active live ranges then that register is given to this otherwise this is being that
is essentially what this algorithm is. Let us again look at this this is what we
have okay I have put all the intervals over here now again I will illustrate the point.
What happens is that the algorithm the main part of the algorithm goes from this point
to this point to this point to this point and then it will go to this point it will
not consider these intermediate points because no new live range starts in those points right.
So it will be at this point at this point at this point this point and then after it
jumps to here and when it jumps to here it tries to see which live ranges have ended
this live range has ended so it will try to free the register okay.
So let us take this interval put it over here right and then see all the intervals
are sorted in the increasing order live intervals are sorted in the increasing order so it is
S 1 based on the start point so that is S 1 S 2 S 3 S 4 S 5 and S 6 because the start
points are in the increasing order right you can see them to be in the increasing order.
Now initially the active list is empty let us look at this particular point right and
let us assume the case that we have three registers dollar 1 dollar 2 and dollar 3.
Now S 1 can be assigned the register dollar 1 right then we come to the next point S 2
no interval has expired before this right now S 2 can be assigned the register because
you have a free register right so dollar 2 can be assigned now that also has to be
put into the active list and then you sort the active list in terms of the end time okay.
So when you come to S 3 you have active list as S 1, S 2 right and when you come to S 3
no more live ranges have expired so that is fine have nothing else to do.
Now you look at your free register pool you have one free register which is available
that can be given to S 3 now the active is S 1, S 2, S 3 but if you arrange it in terms
of the end point it will be S 1, S 3 and then S 2 correct so the active and the next point
is S 1, S 3 and S 2. Now you do not have any more free registers
and when you are at S 4 no live range is ending either so you have nothing to release right.
So at this point in time you have to make a decision about spill right because you have
no free registers you consider the end point so now you look at your active list which
is the last one in that S 2 when does S 2 end point end yeah as opposed to this S 4
ends earlier correct. So now because S 4 end point is less than S 2 end point you
decide to spill S 2 the idea here is that the one which has the longest live interval
if you spill then you can accommodate several variables with that spill right.
So you spill S 2 and assign that register to S 4 so when you come to point S 5 this
is the first point where you see that one live interval has ended so you can say now
you can remove S 1 from the active list and you can put back that register into free registers
right so you have one free register which is available and that can be given to S 5
alright. So then you come to S 6 by that time S 3 and S 4 have ended so you can free those
registers and then you can assign one register to S right.
So this is essentially how this linear scan algorithm works jumps from one start point
of an interval to the next start point and so on and at every point in time whenever
it has to make a decision about spill it considers the live interval of the variable for which
it wants to allocate the register with the live interval of the last variable which is
in the active list which is S 2 whichever one is further that is spilled the other one
is given the register. If S 2 had been smaller right or all of them are of the same distance
then you would have decided to spill S 4 and S 4 would not have been allocated. So that
kind of completes our discussion in register allocation that is really what we wanted to
do. There is something that I will talk about as far as the interaction between register
allocation and instruction scheduling that we will take it up later okay.
So I think it is time to close so essentially what we have seen yeah have a question.
Oh okay so I have not really talked about those kinds of things if S 2 appears to be
a left operand of something or let us say if you are talking about doing this for a
risk architecture eventually S 2 has to be loaded into a register so you will incur a
cost for that right all right. So again you must understand that yesterday we talked about
static single assignment right so when you do static single assignment that actually
does a lot of things to live ranges and the interference graph sorry the interference
essentially becomes much simpler to handle because again there will be no holes and things
like that. So again that makes register allocation much faster but the traditional way of looking
at it is this graph coloring based approach which is later on modified by this linear
scan approach but the linear scan approach is inefficient in the sense that it does lot
of approximation and therefore even though it does a faster allocation it may do inefficiently
right that is really what we need to understand here.