right. So we are saying if you look at this code here m was m as x and y top top on the
left branch x is 2 y is 3 right branch x is 3 y is 2 what is the meet bottom bottom 2
meet 3 is bottom 3 meet 2 is bottom. So here z will be bottom right if I had not eagerly
done the meet here and come like this what would have been z 5 and if I come this way
what would have been z 5. So what happened I mean even though it is a constant even though
it is a the value of z is a constant we could not identify using our technique and the reason
being and the reason being that the constant propagation the way we are doing is not distributive
that is if we take the flow function here take the flow function here take a meet is
not same as is not same as doing this one first and then this one and taking a meet.
What we are saying if I take this is f1 this is f2 right if I do f1 first then f2 and then
take a meet and then do f3 that is not same as f3 on f1 meet f3 on f2 take a minute to chew
over it if this is f1 if the flow function is f1 f2 f3 I am doing f1 f2 take a meet and then
f3 that is f3 on I am invoking f3 on meet of f1 and f2 we are saying that is not same as f3 of f1
f3 of f1 meet f3 of f2 both all of them start with the same m0 some initial map right so that
way what we are saying this constant propagation the way we are doing is not distributive over the
meet right so we will lose a few constants here we are not losing constants because we are
impregnated I mean one of the condition is never taken or anything here the conditions
can be taken even then the value of Z should have been I mean we know it is 5 but the way
we are doing is bottom right oh yeah okay okay okay okay okay yeah good reminder so during the
in the lab yeah our friend asks that I have Z equal to 1 here I do constant propagation I get
1 here then I can do loop invariant code motion this can go out and then I can throw away the
one of the Z's because the outer Z this Z equal to 1 this definition reaches nowhere right then
she says so this is the order we follow constant propagation then loop invariant code motion then
do reaching definition it so turns out this is not necessarily the best order among all the
optimizations we study you will see the ordering is a big pain is a big problem if you do a followed
by B sometimes it is good sometimes it is good if you do B followed by A there are times there
are some optimizations where it is well understood that whether you do a followed by B or B followed
by A it is going to be suboptimal unless you do them together okay so such problems such
optimizations where there is a dependent cyclic dependency or like a a depends on B B depends
on A this called as a phase ordering problem so there are some optimizations which have a
phase ordering relation between themselves okay so in this case we said hey this is good to do
maybe sometimes you may want to do some reaching definition so that you can throw away some
unnecessary definitions and then that may lead to some optimization so the there are some optimizations
which are invoked many times because you do not want to do all of them together proceed writing
each optimization first pass itself is complicated now writing something together is much more
complicated so compiler writers in what they do they write individual optimizations they just
invoke it few more bunch of times so how many times so I mean this is kind of now lot of
engineering expertise gets into so those of you care there is a book called much Nick compiler
design modern compiler design if I'm not wrong the first page it shows the the flow chart of
the different optimizations that are that are followed in the HP compiler GCC follows a slightly
different structure but it's pretty hairy lot of so yeah so in this case we did in this order
but you cannot keep on applying them forever right for example in the first example we looked
at we kept doing again and again and again so when do you stop yeah so then it will take yeah so
why author way author way saying why don't we do one thing let us try to reach a fixed point here
let me take one do to do do do do till the end something changed again take this keep on
feeding it to the same thing that's also not there are two challenges there number one the
time how much time are you ready to give for compilation right and then there are optimization
phases where one does X the other does X prime so it may keep changing some some bit then let's
say you say no no let me not let me drop those things which are kind of going against each other
but only focus on that yes as long as it's changing I'll keep on doing the time takes a
lot of time okay yeah okay any questions on the distributive nature of this all right correct
it doesn't matter right okay let's say let's take a guess let's say we are building some
database software say Oracle right take a guess how much time it may take to compile that huh I
couldn't hear you I heard some one I didn't hear the unit I'm sorry no no let's say we
have a powerful computer pick you tell me what are the server class machine on which they will
compile it's the order of days if it is in the order of days your comp if it takes to compile
just one round now you want to do multiple rounds it's kind of pretty we are talking about a
tough thing and the worst part is when I start compiling in the compilation phase you have seen
right I start with high level code then one IR then lower level then lower level then I reached
a very low level IR and finally machine code and there some more optimizations are done now if you
want me to again optimize that then I have to again get back the structure which is which may
not be I'm not be able to do all the high-level optimizations all the high-level IR I may not
be able to reach there at all I'm saying assuming you reach it takes a lot of time but reaching
there itself is hard so pretty much no compiler does this forever because I mean practically
it's much harder I do not know yeah it depends on the optimizations I do not have a reason to say
it will not terminate I do not have a reason to say reason to say it will terminate depends on
the optimizations involved so I do not have enough information to make a comment on that right
so what we are seeing the constant propagation is not distributed an interesting property to
note okay let's look at a piece of code we said as part of optimizing an if condition we said if
we have code like this if I know the condition is true I can throw in the then or the else part
but that is another optimization constant propagation is another optimization during
constant propagation let us say I had some I here not necessarily one some value during constant
propagation I found that at this point value of I is going to be one now I need to do something
otherwise during constant if I do constant propagation like this let's say it's I equal
to some case some computation and I found I equal to one and then if I do not deal with the then
and else part I will say J is not a constant here right why because J is one year J is two
year meet is bottom correct now you may say look let me do one pass of constant propagation
where here till here I will get I equal to one right so I have a statement I equal to one then
invoke if simplification come back do constant propagation again good so I did this then let
us say there is some more if part inside then here then again do constant propagation again
do if switching if simplification keep on doing it will take lot of time right so what we will do
we will do something called conditional constant propagation as an extension to the basic Kildar's
algorithm that we talked about so this is this is the 1975 paper and an extension that we may if
we have time we will go over an extension of this 91 paper this 91 paper we are talking about
Wegman and Jadak paper we will go over this work and if possible an extension to that if time permits
okay so what's the idea during the constant propagation algorithm execution if I find that
branch is see at this moment I may say that hey only the then branch can be taken right then why
should I process the else branch see the J became a bottom here because both the L then and else
branches were both processed at this point I know that only if I know that only the then branch
will be taken why should I add the else branch to my work list that's the basic intuition let
me add only those branches which are which I know will be taken right if I know that only one branch
will be taken then let me add that branch during processing if I find that no no the else branch
will also be taken then I will add that but let me not add them eagerly let me evaluate the condition
depending on the condition add either the then branch or the else branch or both depending upon
the value of the condition the intuition is clear so I see all types of head shakes some
like this some like this some like this some like this so that that's pretty confusing do we have
a yes good so this is something that you have seen right I mean the head shakes the traditional
understanding is this is yes this is no we also have this and sometimes we have I mean an eight
type of I know so what does it mean maybe or don't care how it's a bottom I have no clue what's happening
bottom would be okay okay okay we will try to take this intuition that we had so far and now
we will design an algorithm so what's the main idea with each block I will have a Boolean flag
that says is the block executable or not I will process only executable blocks if they are in
my work list if a block is not executable I will not process it okay so to start I again I am saying
I'll only process the blocks which are marked executable to start I will only process the entry
node so let me be kind and mark it as executable okay if I processed one node you have processed
one node that means it is executable after processing this node what should I do let yeah
so one point so either there is a condition at the end of it that means it will have multiple
successors or there is only one successors both are possible so if I am if I am processing a node
and this node has only one successor that means if I am executed executable my successor will also
be executable right so if the current node has only one successor that means if I am executed
my successor will definitely be executed so let me after my after finishing my execution I will
also mark my successor as executable right if I have multiple successors then what that means
I may if my basic block ends with a condition the condition can be true or false let me do
one thing like I did here this condition is always of the form either y of z or some Boolean right
so let me look up this Boolean value in my constant propagation map constant map in the
map if it is true I will mark the then branch as executable if it is false I will mark the
else branch as executable if it is bottom both as executable if it is stop I will mark none as
I will not touch them right what I am saying I will evaluate the condition during the constant
propagation using the current constants map if the constants map tells me that can we close
the laptop if you are not using it to take notes if my constant in my constant map tell
me that the condition will evaluate to a constant then I will take either the then branch if it is
true and if it is false I will take the else branch rather I will mark them as executable once
they mark them then they will be processed in the and remember I am not changing once I mark it
executable later I am not coming and saying oh hey I will make it non executable once I mark it
executable it remains executable and this is consistent with our idea of monotonic progress
where if I have true now in future it will not become false now it is true in future it can remain
true or become bottom similarly now if we now if it is false in future it can be false or bottom
but it will never become only true correct okay and we will iterate till there is no change I
have now two lists one sorry I have two things to keep in mind has my because of my basic block
did the constant map change or did any new block became executable even if my constant map has
not changed if some exit new block has become executable then also I want to continue processing
okay what we will do we will take the previous example for this and one more on the board and
try to do it okay so in this case what is my M here let us say I am J I is top J is top after
this statement 1 comma top so now this was executable right after this is processed I
will mark just the this block the header I will evaluate the header because this so let us draw
the CFG for that rate the CFG would be oh I am asked to write only on one side so my CFG would
be right so now I I mark this one as executable process this right what is
the end of processing this my M will be 1 comma top I J and now since it has two successors I
will check the condition is a condition true the answer is yes then I will mark this as executable
okay and then I will process this so after processing this it will be 1 comma 1 right
after processing this it has only one successor so I will mark this guy as executable so here
it will be it came as 1 comma 1 it goes out as 1 comma 1 it has no successor so I will stop and
now I will do so my constant identification is done I will make one more pass and wherever
the constants are there I just replace so the here this is a constant I will replace it with
1 here I will replace it with 1 comma 1 I have not removed this part now you can do a so the
constant application 1 equal to 1 will become 0 sorry it will become true right so now I have
a code that looks like this I equal to 1 if true do this false do that now I can do if
simplification well if simplification job is to only remove the just look at the condition and
throw away unreachable code right trivially unreachable code so now this can go away make
sense if you are fine we will take an example and want you to let me see if I can write the
example here itself oh this guy doesn't like to add blank pages is it now this is not going to
let me write I am bad at doing that this is going to be fun you will see some interesting
aspects
we will do in steps in the same we will just take the same code and write
yeah some minor addition to that code so do this until some condition and then print ij
let's let's see what constants do we get
keep an eye on your what is executable okay okay for each statement keep marking
okay okay so okay you know fault here
good question so she says all these optimations we are talking about it just because the programmer
has been extremely lacks in writing the program if he had done his job well then probably it
wouldn't have happened the answer is yes and no I think it's worth telling a story here in
1950s when the first compilers came into existence people started pushing for using compilers
programmers hated it programmers said no we will not use the compiler I can write better code than
the compiler okay okay so as the program became bigger and bigger it was becoming very challenging
for the programmer to write very efficient code but in those days programs weren't as big and
the program and the compiler was not getting getting as optimized code for those small codes
but slowly the compiler optimization became more and more powerful the program became bigger so
the programmer just couldn't manage like keeping it modular you can optimize individual functions
but what about across functions maybe you are causing a library you have no clue what the library does
the program the compiler knows what the library does what you do you didn't write the library
you didn't write the third party software in industry those who are in industry they
are 15 member team each person is writing different code right and all of these is compiled together
right so yes if the optimizer will have no work to do right because they got a library code whatever is done is already done it
there examples we are giving on the other hand are deliberately toy examples right because
because I am putting them up on the fly and but if you look at the real world programs you will see tons of these things
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah done done so what is it?
I will be constant is it?
true true so you mark this as executable when you do I equal to I plus 1 what is the value of I?
2 good good no no if it is true what is the value of I?
it will be 2 how?
because of I plus 1 no you will do a meet here and that will be?
bottom bottom and then which one will be executable?
this will be executable no no
so if it is bottom both are executable if it is bottom both are executable
so mark both of them as executable and then?
are we done?
yes sir bottom bottom how are we?
sir I am confused like when I am taking the plan I will definitely mark this as executable
and next round the value of the data is going to follow
you got I equal to 1 you missed the I plus plus
so now what will happen?
value of I will be?
it will remain it will be?
it will be what?
it will become 2 and then?
no from here you will come to the while condition and while condition you can go either here
or here which is executable?
it will consider both of them as?
no what is the value of I?
I equal to 1 and now I have to mark both the parts
make sense?
make sense and once you take both the parts what will happen?
how are we doing?
how did you mark both as executable?
I is 1 so J equal to 1 therefore I mark this
I becomes 2 here and then?
condition and then you are going back to beginning
so what is the value of I at the beginning?
sir you go here
yeah what is the value of I?
no
sir you are making I equal to
you made I equal to but at this block how many predecessors does this block have?
no this block has 2 predecessors
coming from top and coming from here
so you are taking meet of?
1 and 2
meet of 1 and 2 will be?
no
the constant of the relation I have any two constants
they are different depending on the meet they will become bottom
so I will become bottom
if I become bottom what will happen?
if I become bottom it will take the value which is recent
no it will take bottom because we cannot keep only the rate
see when I have to start processing a block
I have to compute it in M
what is the in M in this statement?
whatever is coming in it has two predecessors
sir you are taking meet
right?
make sense?
yeah
so if it is bottom what will you do?
take the meet of 1 and 2
see right?
so I is bottom then what will you do after that?
so at this point value of I is bottom
value of J is 1
what will you do then?
continue processing
may I?
value of I is bottom and J is 1
because that is what has come
so from here I equal to 2 and J equal to 1 came
and you take a meet with
I equal to 2 J equal to 1
this is coming from one branch
from the top branch what am I getting?
1 and J equal to top
what do I get?
meet
I equal to bottom J equal to 1
one meet top is 1
so now you take this and process this statement
process this condition
is the condition true or false here?
should be false
no we do not know
what is the value of I?
I is bottom
so is it true or false?
no no no
we do not know that
if we know it
so in round 1
it was top top
after I equal to 1 it became
one top
I will evaluate this condition
so this was executable
I marked this as executable
then this is marked as executable
this is marked as executable
and I equal to 1
true or false? true
which one will I mark as executable?
I will mark this as executable
so here it was 1 comma top
so after executing
so here also it was 1 comma top
after executing this it became?
I am just marking it here in and this is out was?
1 comma 1
okay
after executing this
how many success this guy has?
1 so it will mark
its successor as
who is its successor?
I plus plus this guy so this is marked as executable
these two are not marked executable yet
then what is the in for this?
1 comma 1
after executing it
so 1 comma sorry
it was 1 comma 1
and after executing it became?
2 comma 1
okay how many success it has?
1 it will mark the condition as true
I mean executable
and then I do not know the value of condition it is
some bottom
so I will mark both its successors as?
executable
executable how many successors it has?
the print and
the do
so mark this
now I have to process
see the out of this guy it was initially
top top it became 2 1
right
so when I add these two
they are not only marked executable
but their in has changed
so I will look at its previous in
okay previous in was
something now it is changed
now it will
again I have to compute its new in anyway
how do I compute its new in?
how many predecessors this guy has?
I will take a meet of its
in
from left side
in from both the branches
so I will take a meet of 1 comma top
and 2 comma 1
which will be meet of 1 and 2 is?
bottom
and top and 1 is?
now I will process
if i equal to equal to 1
so incoming is bottom comma 1
what is the value of i?
bottom is the value of i is bottom
what is the value of this expression?
bottom
there is nothing called
don't know there is nothing called
there is
I only all my expressions take
values of constants
top or bottom
that is the only values I can have
right
so if i is bottom this expression is
value is bottom
which one will I mark as executable?
both
okay
so I will take j equal to 1
something as j
since it was
different from what I had before
so after executing this
it was it took bottom comma 1
and output will be
bottom comma 1
here the input was bottom comma 1
output will be?
no
no output of j equal to
after j processing j equal to
bottom bottom
no
bottom 2
right side is 2 here
right side is 2
so if initially j could be bottom
but after processing j equal to 2 it is
so it is bottom 2
now there is a join point here
so processing i plus plus
it has two predecessors
in the previous case the predecessor was giving
only bottom because I was not processing it
it was only giving me top for
from its side
but now I have one side bottom 1
the other side bottom 2
so the in for this i plus plus is
bottom bottom
bottom
in comes bottom bottom
if I do i plus plus
what is the value of i when the old value was
bottom bottom
so the output is bottom comma bottom
after this I come to while
so now that all are marked
executable I won't talk about
what is being marked as executable
I will only see is there any change
so previously
it was 2 comma 1 now it is bottom bottom
right
so I come here
something has changed
I will say okay
hey add this guy and this guy
to my work list this is already there in my work list
let me add the do
let me take now a meet
to process this do statement
I have to take a meet of
its predecessors so what is the meet
of the what are the predecessors from here
it is going bottom bottom from top I am
getting 1 comma
1 comma top
so what is the meet of bottom comma
bottom bottom
in is bottom bottom
out is also bottom bottom
and now
is it different
from what was there before
yes
it was this was before this is new
so something has changed
so I will process this
and I will its output
output is also changed bottom bottom
so I will process this
if I process this
in comes
sorry in comes bottom bottom
out is
bottom one
bottom one good
this same as this
bottom one and bottom one
nothing has changed
so this guy says I do not need
to add my successor because
I mean nothing has changed
but the way we have done
we are saying if my
in has changed add
my successor
my successor will decide whether to proceed further
or not so what I will do I will
mark I will say hey do process this
we will hold on to that
and similarly j comma 2 this j2
in comes bottom bottom
out goes
bottom two and at the meet
it becomes bottom bottom
now this i plus plus
will say hey my in previously was
bottom bottom now is also
bottom bottom nothing has changed
so it will not add anymore
what is there in my work list only this print
so print the in
comes bottom bottom
it is not
assignment statement so nothing changes
second iteration
second iteration here
one two three four
bottom one in came bottom
comma one out was bottom
comma two
yes see if I do not know what
it can be let us say it is a function that
I library code or some function
call or something that I do not know
then what will I assume
it could be true or false
right
bottom everyone
on the same page
if you look at it
even though during the
analysis the middle of it
it you had
a case of hey something becoming true
only the
then branch was becoming true
later
both became true
some of you said
no no no
where is the code
yeah some of you said
erase that code is it fine
code is here code is here some of you said
in the second iteration
value of i will be two
at the beginning no
value of i will not be two
after meet it will become bottom
value of i is two here
but after meet it became
bottom otherwise think about
this way if you keep if you do not take
the meet the value of i will keep on
increasing
right one question
that might come to your mind
what if the loop never terminates
in practice in
what if the loop is such that
this is here
what if it is this
this is the
code while true
you know it to be true
what will you do
the execute will not become executable
okay that is fine
so what you are saying the print will not become executable
okay
but the question is will you terminate
no i will terminate
yeah terminate
so the question is
in the modified example
my while
has only true
has its condition
so will i terminate
the yeses are still murmurs
here few murmuring
no's as well
i want a firm
yes or a firm
no
i still hear both
so those
who are saying yes
can you give a reason why it is yes
or rather let me do the other way around
those who are saying no
can you say why it say no
why it won't terminate
why you fear that it won't terminate
i is constantly
changing
let us see what will happen
i start i equal to 1
right
after it became i plus plus it became
i equal to 2
and then i come back here
because it is true i don't mark this as executable
i come back here
what is the value of i
bottom
because i took a meet of
1 and 2
once it became a bottom
i will
see i did not add this do
this statement back
only because
this was true
i added because
look
something has changed
something has not
changed and i don't care
right
we said
we will keep on iterating till
either a new executable block is added
or something has changed
this is already executable
it is marked executable even before
i am not resetting its executable
it is a mutable bit
right
those who are saying
yes it will definitely terminate
not just in this example but any example
what is the argument
we will draw everything will
is it gapped
let's start it would change
if it doesn't change then it would terminate
good
the key is let us say some variables values
do not change
for example let's say there is no i++
the value of i is
not changing what will happen
it will remain 1
value of j
will in this case remain 1
but will we terminate
will we terminate
why will we terminate
no change
because there is no change
make sense
yes good
if value of i keeps on changing
then
exactly
after some
after few steps of our analysis
we have finite values
that i can take
we cannot take infinite values
for the variables
since it will take finite number of variables
we can take infinite number of variables
since it will take finite number of values
we will terminate
make sense
so it doesn't matter whether user program is an infinite loop or not
we are not an infinite loop
that's a good point
i like this
let's do this
i will make some minor modifications
under some conditions
i will make
aha
i am just being evil
i like it
so value of j
is flipping between
0 and 1
it was 1
it became 0
0 and 1
and
yeah
so okay
my handwriting right
so let me read i equal to 1
j equal to 1
if j equal to equal to 1
i plus plus
and j equal to
flip basically
if it is 0 make it 1 if it is 1 make it 0
and the way the code is designed
both i and j will
keep flipping
we k
our values are
always going in one direction
but now
my i will
my j will flip
and it will flip i
so will i go into infinite loop
so
so initially i will be 0
after one iteration it will be 1
but at the end of the iteration when i take a meat
it will become bottom
let them flip in real
in the real world
in the abstract world
we wont go to infinite loop
are you guys convinced of this
anyone who is not
i can go over it no issues
but this is kind of a very
a beautiful point here
that even though
the values keep on
either increasing decreasing or going back and forth
it is not that
only when it is increasing continuously we will
hit a bottom
for us we are not checking whether it is increasing or not
we are seeing it is different or not